<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>binary.org.uk - Review</title><link href="http://binary.org.uk/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://binary.org.uk/feeds/review.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://binary.org.uk/</id><updated>2018-08-19T18:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Building the PiDP-8 Kit</title><link href="http://binary.org.uk/building-the-pidp-8-kit.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-08-19T18:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-08-19T18:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Joe</name></author><id>tag:binary.org.uk,2018-08-19:/building-the-pidp-8-kit.html</id><summary type="html"></summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here is my experience of building the &lt;a href="http://obsolescence.wixsite.com/obsolescence/pidp-8"&gt;Obsolescence Guaranteed PiDP-8&lt;/a&gt; Kit. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="images/pidp/final.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="Alt text" src="/images/pidp/small/final_small.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won't go over the entire process to build the kit, there's already a lot of information available on Oscars site and plenty of other people have done descriptions of their builds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will however detail some of the issues I had and any changes I made below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PCB and Soldering&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used the chip holder to hold the LEDs in place when soldering - It was quite short (could only hold about 3 LEDs at a time) 
but I just moved it along the row so the previous 2 LEDs were holding the next one in place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I burnt the plastic of one switch with my soldering iron and another switch didn't work when tested. I got two replacement
switches from Oscar but the one I thought wasn't working started working, so I now have a spare :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I noticed some of the screw and solder holes are visible behind the front panel so I masked them up with black tape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/pidp/components.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="Alt text" src="/images/pidp/small/components_small.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="/images/pidp/board1.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="Alt text" src="/images/pidp/small/board1_small.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="/images/pidp/board2.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="Alt text" src="/images/pidp/small/board2_small.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="/images/pidp/board3.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="Alt text" src="/images/pidp/small/board3_small.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="/images/pidp/board4.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="Alt text" src="/images/pidp/small/board4_small.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="/images/pidp/board5.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="Alt text" src="/images/pidp/small/board5_small.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spacewar Panel Test&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;video id="tree" controls preload="auto" width="360" height="240"&gt;
&lt;source src="/videos/spacewar_panel_test.mp4" type='video/mp4'&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mounting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I used the blocks in the way Oscar details. For the long block I tried to test fit the pcb and panel with the block 
underneath - I went with 1mm overhang in the end (2mm would be too much). I figured I could also sand down the block (some
people were reporting it needed to be flush with the pcb with no overhang).
In the end I found the pcb refused to sit up against the right hand side of the case (even with all the screws holding the block) so I had to wedge 
some folded paper in the left hand side to stop the pcb going over to the left.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/pidp/mounting_blocks1.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="Alt text" src="/images/pidp/small/mounting_blocks1_small.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I also shaved of a corner of the long block using a plane so it would not touch the solder points and would sit flat (see photos)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/pidp/mounting_blocks2.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="Alt text" src="/images/pidp/small/mounting_blocks2_small.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="/images/pidp/mounting_blocks3.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="Alt text" src="/images/pidp/small/mounting_blocks3_small.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With the two small blocks I tried to place them as Oscar had in the photo. One of the blocks was conflicting with the solder
points so I had to cut a chunk of the wood out to make it sit flat. It looks a little flimsy now but I don't think it will cause problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/pidp/mounting_blocks4.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="Alt text" src="/images/pidp/small/mounting_blocks4_small.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another problem people report is that the panel does not sit right because the bottom is sitting on top of the switch tags.
I decided to cut of some of the lip using some craft knifes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finishing touches&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also found the panel wouldn't fit very well without bending outwards, so I also had to shave some bamboo at the sides. 
Where I had been struggling to fit it some of the panel markings came off around the edge. 
Using some black paint on the panel I went over these and it made it look a lot better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made a hole in the top corner - this seemed the most sensible since the pi zero connectors are there and it was the shortest distance to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/pidp/rear.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="Alt text" src="/images/pidp/small/rear_small.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the power cable I used a USB cable with an integrated switch. I thought having a USB connector made more sense
as it meant I could power it from pretty much anything with a USB port.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to get one of the usb/ethernet hubs as Oscar had and mount on the back, this lights up blue when the pi is powered
meaning it doubles up as a discrete power light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/pidp/usb_hub_and_serial.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="Alt text" src="/images/pidp/small/usb_hub_and_serial_small.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I added some plastic feet on the bottom to stop it moving when the switches are used.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/pidp/feet.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="Alt text" src="/images/pidp/small/feet_small.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Serial port&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wanted to be able to connect to the PiDP-8 but didn't want to rely on the wireless as being the only way.
Enabling the serial port seemed like a lot of hassle so I went with the USB serial ttl route as Oscar suggested. 
Instead of 2 cables I ended up getting 1 cable plus another unit built into a stick with the pins on it.
This meant I could plug it into the hub and wire up the cable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we are running &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colossal_Cave_Adventure"&gt;"Adventure"&lt;/a&gt; in a terminal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="images/pidp/adventure.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="Alt text" src="/images/pidp/small/adventure_small.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a great little project.
The soldering work is not difficult at all assuming you have some basic soldering skills.
There are a few places you might get caught out but as long as you read through Oscar's notes several times and plan ahead you shouldn't have any big issues. &lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>